Rudberg Research Collection of the Central New England Railway 2008.0043
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
Rudberg Research Collection of the Central New England Railway
2002-2013
2008.0043
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
0.75 Linear feet
The collection consists of tour guidebooks compiled by Bernard L. Rudberg of photocopies of photographs, maps, correspondence, and documents related to the history of the Central New England Railway, which ran from Maybrook, New York, to Hartford, Connecticut, in the period between 1898 and 1927, at which point it was taken over by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. Mr. Rudberg creates the books for the participants of an annual guided bus tour he coordinates, in April or May of each year beginning in 2002, that follows portions of the old railway line, and provides information about the towns on the route, train wrecks that occurred, old carbarns, turntables and roundhouses, and such features as the Poughkeepsie River Bridge.
Rudberg, Bernard L.
Biography
Bernard L. Rudberg is a resident of Wappinger Falls, New York, and author of Twenty-five Years on the ND&C: a History of the Newburgh, Dutchess & Connecticut Railroad ( Fleischmanns, N.Y.: Purple Mountain Press, 2002). He is the coordinator of an annual bus tour of the defunct railroad line of the Central New England Railway and its predecessor and successor railroad lines.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of tour guidebooks, each with over 200 pages, compiled by Bernard L. Rudberg consisting of photocopies of photographs, maps, correspondence, and documents related to the history of the Central New England Railway, which ran from Maybrook, New York, to Hartford, Connecticut, in the period between 1898 and 1927, at which point it was taken over by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. Mr. Rudberg creates the books for the participants of an annual guided bus tour he coordinates, in April or May of each year beginning in 2002, that follows portions of the old railway line, and provides information about the towns on the route, train wrecks that occurred, old carbarns, turntables and roundhouses, and such features as the Poughkeepsie River Bridge.
Predecessor railroad lines of the Central New England Railway included the Clove Branch Railroad, the Connecticut Western Railroad, the Dutchess & Columbia Railroad, the Dutchess County Railroad, the Hartford & Connecticut Western Railroad, the New York & Massachusetts Railroad, the New York & New England Railroad, the Newburgh, Dutchess & Connecticut Railroad, the Philadelphia, Reading & New England Railroad, the Poughkeepsie & Connecticut Railroad, and the Poughkeepsie & Eastern Railroad.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of New England railroad history materials. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated by Mr. Bernard L. Rudberg between 2002 and 2013.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Central New England Railway.; Clove Branch Railroad Company.; Connecticut Western Railroad; Dutchess & Columbia Railroad.; Dutchess County Railroad.; Hartford and Connecticut Western Railroad.; New York & Massachusetts Railroad.; New York & New England Railroad; New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Company.; Newburgh, Dutchess and Connecticut Railroad; Philadelphia, Reading & New England Railroad Company; Poughkeepsie & Connecticut Railroad.; Poughkeepsie & Eastern Railroad Company; Connecticut; History; New York (State); New York--Poughkeepsie--Poughkeepsie Railroad Bridge; Photocopies; Railroads
- Research Collection, 2002-2010
  - Tour guidebook, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Tour guidebook, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Tour guidebook, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Tour guidebook, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Tour guidebook, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Tour guidebook, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Tour guidebook, 2008 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Tour guidebook, 2009 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Tour guidebook, 2010 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Tour guidebook, 2011 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Tour guidebook ( Norfolk, Connecticut, to the New York State line), 2012 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Tour guidebook, 2013 April 7